在本节和下节中，我想给大家展示两个非常犀利的攻击
In this segment and the next, I wanna show
you two very cute attacks on deployed
针对认证加密系统的攻击。不过首先我们先回顾一下
authenticated encryption systems. But
first let's do a quick recap. So recall
记得认证加密意味着系统提供CPA安全性
that authenticated encryption means that
the system provides CPA security plus
已经密文完整性。认证加密还意味着
cipher text integrity. And authenticated
encryption means that we can preserve
我们可以在有主动攻击者存在的情况下，保持私密性
confidentiality in the presence of an
active adversary, and moreover, the
攻击者甚至不能以任何方式修改密文，且不被检测到
adversary can't modify the cipher text in
any way without being detected. We also
我们还证明了认证加密可以阻止这些非常强大的
showed that authenticated encryption
prevents these very powerful chosen cipher
选择密文攻击。不幸的是，认证加密有一个很重要的局限性
text attacks. Unfortunately, authenticated
encryption has a pretty significant
那就是它不能承受不好的实现
limitation in that it simply can't help a
bad implementation. If you implement
如果不正确地实现认证加密，那么你的实现
authenticated encryption incorrectly, then
your implementation will be vulnerable to
对主动攻击将是脆弱的。我们看标准机制
active attacks. And then we looked at
standards constructions. I mentioned these
我提到过这三个标准可以提供认证加密。我想指出
three standards that provide authenticated
encryption. And I want to point out, when
实际中，当你需要使用认证加密时
you need to use authenticated encryption
in practice, you should just be using one
你应该就使用这三个标准中的一个。
大家不应该试图去自己实现认证加密
of these three standards. You shouldn't
try to implement authenticated encryption
我希望本节给大家看的这个攻击
by yourself, and I hope that the attack
that I'll show you in this segment
能够说服大家，实现不是你应该自己去做的
convinces you that this is not something
you should do yourself. Just use one of
就用GCM, CCM或EAX。但是，知道一点也好
GCM, CCM or EAX. However, it's good for
you to know that in general, when you want
一般情况下，当你想提供认证加密时，正确的方法是先加密
to provide authenticated encryption, the
correct way to do things is encrypt, then
然后再计算MAC，因为这样无论你组合什么加密和MAC算法
MAC, because then no matter which
encryption and MAC algorithms you combine.
得到的结果将是认证加密
The result will be authenticated
encryption, again assuming the encryption
假定这里的加密和MAC算法是正确实现的
and MAC algorithm are implemented
correctly. Okay, so let's look at a very
我们看一个非常犀利的针对TLS记录协议的攻击。
特别地，当使用CBC加密时
acute attack on the TLS record protocol.
In particular, when CBC encryption is
我来简要提醒一下TLS解密的工作方式
used. Let me just briefly remind you that
the way TLS decryption works, is, first of
首先，到来的密文是CBC加密的
all, an incoming cipher text is CBC
decrypted. Then the next thing that
然后，接下来实现的程序会检查补齐格式是否正确
happens is the implementation will check
if the pad has the correct format. For
比如说，如果补齐长度是5个字节，格式应为55555
example, if the pad is of length five, the
format should be 55555. And if it's not of
如果格式不正确，那么密文被拒绝
the correct format. Then the cipher text
is rejected. So this basically checks that
这就是检查解密后的记录的末尾是否含有正确的补齐
the ending of the decrypted record
contains the correct pad. And then if the
如果补齐格式正确，那么接下来检查MAC
pad has the correct format, then the next
thing that happens is that the MAC is
检查信息标签。如果标签不正确
checked, the tag is checked. And if the
tag turns out to be incorrect, again, the
这个记录也会被拒绝。如果标签有效，
那么剩下的数据被认为是可被认证的
record is rejected. If the tag is valid,
then the remaining data is considered to
于是交给应用。那么我想指出
be authentic and is given to the
application. So what I wanted to point out
TLS解密时会发生两种错误。一种是补齐错误
is there are two types of errors in TLS
decryption. One is a padding error and one
另一种是MAC错误。实际上有一点很重要，
那就是不要告诉攻击者
is a MAC error. And it turns out it's very
important that the adversary not be told
发生了哪种错误。我简单解释一下为什么
which of these errors occurred. And let me
briefly explain why. So, suppose an
假设攻击者可以区分这两种错误，换句话说
attacker can actually differentiate the
two types of errors. In other words, he
攻击者可以知道是发生了补齐错误，还是MAC错误。
得到的结果我们叫做
can tell if a pad error occurred, or a MAC
error occurred. The result is what we call
补齐神谕。试想一下攻击者截获了一段特定的密文
the padding oracle. Cause now, imagine
the adversary has a certain cipher text
攻击者想试着解密这段密文
that it intercepted. And it wants to try
and decrypt that cipher text. What it
他可以把这份密文提交给服务器
could do, is it could take that cipher
text as is, and submit it to the server.
服务器会解密这段密文，然后检查
The server is gonna decrypt the cipher
text and then look to see if the pad has
补齐格式是否正确。如果补齐格式不正确
the correct format. If the pad doesn't
have the correct format, we'll get one
我们会得到一种错误类型。如果补齐格式正确，
由于这段随机密文是攻击者捏造的
type of error. If the pad has the correct
format, it's very likely since this is
很有可能MAC是错误的
just some random cipher text that the
adversary concocted himself, it's very
然后攻击者会观测到一个MAC错误
likely the MAC will be incorrect, and then
the adversary will observe a MAC error. So
所以如果补齐无效，我们会看到一个补齐错误；
而如果补齐有效
if the pad is invalid, we'll see a pad
error, whereas if the pad is valid we'll
我们会看到一个MAC错误。因此，在向服务器提供密文后
see a MAC error. As a result, the
adversary, after submitting the cipher
攻击者可以知道解密的密文中的最后几个字节
text to the server, the adversary can tell
whether the last bytes in the decrypted
是否是有效的补齐。换句话说
cipher text have a valid pad or not. In
other words, whether the last bytes in the
解密的密文中的最后几个字节是否为1，22，333，
或4444，等等。。
decrypted cipher text are end with one. Or
2-2, or 3-3-3, or 4-4-4-4, and so on. So
这样攻击者就学到了解密的密文中的一些信息
the adversary learns something about the
decrypted cipher text, just by submitting
仅仅是通过提交密文给服务器。这是个漂亮的例子
the cipher text to the server. So this is
a beautiful example of what's called a
叫做选择密文攻击的例子。攻击者提交密文
chosen cipher text attack. Where again,
the adversary submits the cipher
然后他能学习到解密后所得明文的一些信息
text and then he gets to learn something
about the resulting plain text. And now
现在问题是，攻击者能否使用这个信息来完全解密
the question is whether he can use that
information to completely decrypt a given
一个给定的密文？我想给大家展示，一个补齐神谕
cipher text. And I want to show you that a
padding oracle can actually be used to
可以被用来完全解密一个给定的密文。
在展示之前，我想提醒大家
completely decrypt a given cipher text.
But before I say that, I want to remind
老版本的TLS实际上在对付返回的警告信息里
you that older versions of TLS actually
leaked the type of error simply in the
泄漏了错误类型。发送不同的警告类型
alert message that was sent back to the
peer. Different types of alerts were sent
根据发生了什么类型的错误。这种攻击出现后
depending on which type of error occurred.
As soon as this attack came out, SSL
SSL的实现总是简单地输出同一类型的错误
implementations simply always reported the
same type of error, so just looking at the
所以只看警告类型不能让攻击者知道发生了哪种错误
alert type wouldn't tell the adversary
which error occurred. Nevertheless, there
不过，依然有一个补齐神谕。那么我来解释为什么
was still a padding oracle. So let me
explain why. So this was observed by Canvel
这是由Canvel等人发现的，Canvel等人发现
TLS解密的实现方式中
et. al. Canvel et. al. realized that
the way TLS decryption is implemented is
首先，记录被解密，然后检查补齐
first of all, the record is decrypted,
then the pad is checked, and if the pad is
如果补齐无效，解密中止并产生一个错误；如果补齐有效
invalid, decryption is aborted and an
error is generated. If the pad is valid.
检查MAC。如果MAC无效，解密中止
Then the MAC is checked. And then if the
Mac is invalid, decryption is aborted, and
并产生一个错误。因此，这就造成了一个计时攻击
an error is generated. As a result, this
causes a timing attack. You realize that
大家发现，如果补齐无效，那么警告信息很快就会发出
if pad is invalid, then the alert message
is sent very quickly. And you notice here,
大家注意，在21毫秒内，密文会被拒绝
that, in fact, you see that, within 21
milliseconds, the cipher text is rejected.
但是，如果补齐有效，那么就要检查MAC了
However, if the pad is valid, then now the
MAC needs to be checked, and when it's
发现MAC是无效的，警告仅在这点生成
discovered to be invalid, the alert is
only generated at that point. In other
换句话说，在这种情况下，会花稍微多一点的时间，
直到生成警告
words, then in that case it takes a little
bit longer until the alert is generated,
大家看到，这平均花掉23毫秒
and you see that on average this takes
about 23 milliseconds. So even though the
所以即使对付返回同样的警告，攻击者可以观察
same alert is sent back to the peer. The
adversary can simply observe the time
警告信息生成的用时。如果时间较短
until the alert message is generated. If
the time is short, it knows the pad was
他就知道补齐是无效的。如果时间较长，
他就知道补齐有效，但MAC无效
invalid. If the time is long, it knows the
pad was valid, but the MAC was invalid.
因此，攻击者依然有一个补齐神谕可以告诉他
And as a result the adversary still has a
padding oracle that can tell it whether
补齐是否有效。那么现在我们看如何利用补齐神谕
the pad was valid or invalid. So now let's
see how to use a padding oracle. So I
我说，如果攻击者有一个特定的密文C
claim that if the attacker has a certain
cipher text C, he can completely decrypt
他可以只使用补齐神谕就能完全解密这个密文。
我们来看怎么做
the cipher text just using the padding
oracle. So let's see how to do it. And
作为一个例子，假设攻击者想获取明文M1，换句话说
just as an example, suppose he wants to
obtain M1, in other words, a decryption of
密文第二个分组的解密结果。我们看他用什么
the second block of the cipher text. So
let's see what he would use. So here we
那么这里我们有攻击者截获的密文
have the cipher text that the attacker
intercepted. And this just happens to be
这正好是密文的解密。我写下这个的原因是
the decryption of that cipher text. And
the reason I wrote this down is I wanted
我想让大家记住CBC解密是如何工作的。
大家应该记住
you to remember how CBC decryption works.
So you should keep in mind that one cipher
一个密文分组被直接异或到下一分组的解密结果中
text block is directly XORed into
the decryption of the next cipher text
那么这里攻击者就想知道这部分的明文
block. Okay, so the adversary here wants
to basically learn just this part of the
他这样做。首先他扔掉C2
plain text. So, here's what he's gonna do.
So first of all he's going to throw away
这样最后分组就是C1，即攻击者感兴趣的、想解密的分组
C2 so that, that last block really is just
C1, which is the one he's interested in
现在假设他有一个特定的猜测G，对M1的最后一个字节
decrypting. Now let's suppose that he has
a certain guess, G, for the last byte of
换句话说，他对这最后一个字节有一个猜测
M1, in other words, he just has a guess
for this very, very, very last byte. G is
G是从0到255的某个值。攻击者会做如下事情
a value between zero and 255. What the
attacker will do is the following, he will
他会计算G异或01，再异或分组C0的最后一个字节
C0是前一密文分组
XOR the value G XOR 01 into the last byte
of the block C0, the previous block. Yes
攻击者取前一分组的最后一个字节
so all he did is he took the last byte of
the previous block and XOR that with
把它和他的猜测G异或01进行异或。我们想一想
his guest XOR 01. Now let's think for
just a second and see what happens when
当这两个密文分组被解密时，会发生什么。
不管C0被解密成了什么
this two block cipher text is decrypted.
Well C0 is gonna get decrypted to whatever
也就是些垃圾，我们不用管它
its decrypted to that's just gonna be some
garbage that we don't care about but, now
当C1被解密时，最后一个字节与这个修改的C0异或
when C1 is decrypted the last byte is
gonna be XORed with this modified C0,
得到明文的最后一个字节，将也是
and the result the last byte of the plain
text is gonna be also XORed with this
与这个多出来的、与C0异或的值异或的。
所以这里是实际上原来的
extra value that we stuck into C zero. So
what goes in here is the actual original
明文M1里的最后一个字节。但现在它与"G异或01"异或了
last byte in the plain text M1. But now it
gets XORed with G XOR zero X zero one. So
(0x前缀表示16进制)
现在大家看到，我将这么做。如果M1最后一个字节的猜测G
now you see where I'm going with this. If
the guess G for the last byte of M1 is
是正确的，那么这两项会抵消。最后字节异或G将是0
correct, then these two guys will cancel
one another. Last byte XOR G is just zero.
我们会得到明文的最后一个字节是01。我应当顺便提一下
And what we'll get is the last byte of the
plaintext is just 0x01. I should mention,
0x01是十六进制01的符号表示
by the way, 0x01 just means hex notation
for 01. So literally this is just a one
书面上这是数字1的一个字节的表示。
byte representation of the number one.
Good. So, again, what this means, is if
这意味着，如果我们对M1最后一个字节的猜测是正确的
our guess for the last byte of M1 is
correct, then we get a pad that's well
那么我们获得了一个格式正确的补齐。最后字节仅为1，
以字节1结尾是一个格式正确的补齐，所以
formed. It's just a number one. The number
one is a well formed pad, and therefore,
这个补齐是有效的。补齐神谕说，这个补齐是有效的
the pad is valid. And the padding oracle
will say the pad is valid. If the guess is
如果猜测不正确，那么我们这里会得到一个不等于1的值
incorrect then we'll get a value here
that's not equal to one and then it's very
这次我们的补齐非常有可能是无效的。因此
likely that we have an invalid pad. And as
a result the padding worker will say the
检查补齐时，会说补齐无效。大家看到，如果
我们对M1最后一个字节的猜测是正确的
pad is invalid. So again you see that if
our guess for the last byte of M1 is
我们知道G实际上是正确的猜测
correct, we learn that G was in fact a
correct guess. Whereas if our guess is
而如果我们的猜测是错的，那么我们知道G是错的
incorrect, then we learn that G is an
incorrect guess. So what the attacker is
那么攻击者会创建他的修改后的密文
gonna do is he's gonna create his modified
cipher text. You notice he only modifies
大家注意他只修改密文的第二个分组。
我们把这个发送给补齐神谕
the second block of the cipher text. We're
gonna send this to the padding oracle and
然后根据补齐神谕返回的结果，我们可以知道
then based on the results of the padding
oracle, we learn whether the last byte is
最后一个字节是否等于G。现在我们可以重复这步
equal to G or not. Well, now we can simply
repeat this again and again for G from
G从0遍历到255。这需要256个选择密文询问
zero to 255. This basically requires 256
chosen cipher text queries. Actually, I
实际上平均下来，我们只要做128个选择密文询问
guess on average we'll only have to do 128
chosen ciphers and squares until we find
直到我们找到正确的G。这样我们就知道了M1的最后一个字节
the right G. Then, we learn the last byte
of M1. Well, so now we know the last byte
现在我们知道了M1的最后一个字节。我说，
我们现在可以使用一模一样的流程
of M1. I claim that we can now use the
exact same process to learn the second to
来学到M1中的倒数第二个字节。我问大家，
为了学M1中的倒数第二个字节，我们该用什么补齐？
last byte of M1. Let me ask you, what pad
are we gonna use to learn the second to
不奇怪，不是用字节1
last byte of M1? Well, it shouldn't be
surprising that, instead of just using the
而是用两字节的补齐，包含字节2和2
pad containing the byte one, we're gonna
use a two byte pad containing the bytes
这是一个正确的补齐格式。现在我们可以总是确保
2-2. That's a well formed pad. And now we
can always make sure because we know the
因为我们已知道M1的最后一个字节了。当我们用异或的技巧时
我们可以总是确保明文的最后一个字节
last byte of m1, when we do our XORing trick
we can always make sure that the last byte
为02，现在我们可以猜M1的倒数第二个字节了
of the plain text is in fact 02 and now we
can guess the second to last byte of m2 by
通过尝试很多g的值，直到我们找到那个可以造出补齐22来的g
simply trying lots of values in g until we
find one that makes the pad, in fact, be
通过向补齐神谕提交另外256个询问
0202. And by issuing 256 additional
queries to the padding oracle we will get
我们将学到M1的倒数第二个字节。
现在我们可以一次又一次地迭代这些流程
to learn the second to last byte of m1.
And now we can iterate this again and
因为分组长度为16字节
again, and basically since the length of
the block is sixteen bytes after sixteen
(当然，这里CBC默认使用的是AES)
经过16轮256个询问，我们学到了所有字节
times 256 queries. We get to learn all of
them one. So this is a pretty significant
那么这是一个很重要的攻击，它可以解密TLS记录的分组
attack that is able to decrypt blocks of
the TLS record. So those of you who know
知道TLS内部机制的话，你会抱怨这个攻击不起作用
the inner workings of TLS should complain
that this attack isn't gonna work. The
问题在于当TLS接收到一个带有坏补齐或坏MAC的记录时
problem is that when TLS receives a record
with a bad pad or a bad MAC, it shuts down
它会关闭连接，然后重新协商一个新密钥
the connection, and renegotiates a new
key. As a result, the attacker is now
因此，攻击者现在执着于一段使用旧密钥加密的密文里。
而这个旧密钥不会再被使用了
stuck with a cipher text encrypted using
an old key. And that key is no longer used
所以攻击者无法再提交任何询问。那么TLS中
anywhere, so it cannot submit any more
queries. So with TLS, basically, it can
只能提交一个询问，就是这样。尽管单个询问会泄漏
only submit one query, and that's it. Even
a single query still leaks information
明文信息给攻击者，但它不会暴露整个明文分组M1
about the plain text to the attacker. But
it doesn't expose the entire plain text
但这个攻击如此犀利，以至于只要协议中有这样一个错误
block m1. However this attack is so acute
that whenever there's a mistake like this
就会有某些设定，攻击就会发生
in a protocol there will be some settings
in which it comes up and in this case the
一个IMAP服务器上就有这样的设定。
IMAP是一个流行的阅读电子邮件的协议
setting is in the case of an IMAP server.
So IMAP is a popular protocol for reading
从一个IMAP电子邮件服务器上，通常在IMAP的底层使用TLS协议
email from an IMAP email server, and it's
very common to protect the IMAP protocol
来保护IMAP协议。现在，实际上一个IMAP
by running it on top of a TLS protocol.
Now, it turns out an IMAP. Every five
每5分钟，IMAP客户端会连接到IMAP服务器
minutes, the IMAP client will connect to
the IMAP server, and check whether there's
检查有没有新邮件。方法是先登录IMAP服务器
new email. And the way it does it is by
first logging in to the IMAP server, by
通过发送登陆用户名和密码的信息
sending this login username password
message. And then it goes ahead and check
然后检查是否有新邮件。这意味着每5分钟
if there's new email available. Well, what
this means is that every five minutes, the
攻击者获得一个同样信息的加密
attacker gets an encryption of exactly the
same message in particular, I guess, an
特别的，我猜是密码的加密。那么每5分钟
攻击者可以猜一次包含密码的分组
encryption of the password. And so every
five minutes, it can mount one guess on
如果你的密码是8个字符
the block that contains the password. And
so, if your password is eight characters
攻击者只需要还原这8个字符
long, the attacker simply needs to recover
those eight characters. And he's gonna
他将一次还原一个字节，通过每5分钟猜一次
recover them one byte at, at a time, by
doing one guess per five minutes. And so
Canvel等人证实了在几个小时之内
Canvel et. al. showed that, within a few
hours, you can basically recover the
你可以还原用户密钥。只是通过每5分钟猜一次密码
user's password. Just by mounting one
guess every five minutes. So this is a
这是一个很重要的针对TLS实现的攻击
pretty significant attack against an
implementation of TLS and the defense
防御这个攻击的方法是始终检查MAC，看补齐是否有效
against this was to always check the MAC,
whether the pad is valid or invalid. And
因此需要花同样的反应时间，无论补齐是否有效
as a result it takes the same amount of
time to respond whether the pad is valid
这就防止了计时攻击，让这个攻击更加困难
or invalid. So this removes the timing
attack and makes this attack much harder
这里有两个教训：首先大家注意
to mount. So there are two lessons here.
First of all, you notice that if TLS had
如果TLS先加密后MAC，而不是先MAC后加密
used encrypt then MAC, rather than MAC
then encrypt, then this whole issue would
这个攻击将完全不顶用了，因为如果我先加密后MAC，
那么MAC先被检查
be completely moot, because if I encrypt
then MAC then MAC is checked first, and
然后才解密和检查补齐。先加密后MAC的话
only then does decryption and pad-checking
take place. In encrypt then MAC, the
因为MAC无效，密文就会被扔掉，我们永远不会进行补齐的检查
cipher-text is discarded because the MAC
is invalid and we never even get to a pad
因此，任何对密文的篡改或博弈都会变立即丢弃
check. As a result, any tampering or games
with a cipher-text will be discarded
因为MAC验证失败。另一个要记住的教训是
immediately because the MAC is simply
gonna fail. And second lesson to remember
记得我告诉过大家，MAC和CBC确实提供了认证加密
is that remember I told you that MAC and CBC
actually does provide authenticated
但仅当不透露解密失败的原因。
encryption but only if you don't reveal
why the decryption failed. In this case the
这时，补齐神谕完全破坏了认证加密的性质
padding oracle completely
destroyed the authenticating encryption
我给大家展示了一个利用补齐神谕的攻击
property and basically I showed you an
attack this shows that now this mode does
证实了这种模式不能提供认证加密。
那么我问大家下面的问题
not provide authenticated encryption. So
let me ask you the following question.
假设TLS不使用"先MAC后CBC加密"，而是先计算MAC
Supposing TLS instead of using MAC then
CBC, TLS did MAC then counter mode
再使用计数器模式加密，那么补齐神谕的攻击是否可能？
encryption. Would the padding oracle
attack still be possible or not? The
答案是不可能的，因为计数器模式不使用任何补齐
answer is it wouldn't be possible, simply
because counter-mode doesn't use any
所以在TLS中，这个补齐神谕攻击仅对CBC加密模式有效
padding at all. So this padding oracle
attack only effects CBC encryption modes
TLS也支持计数器模式加密
in TLS. TLS also supports counter-mode
encryption, and counter-mode encryption
而计数器模式加密模式不受这些补齐攻击的影响
modes are simply not affected by these
padding attacks. So that's the end of this
本节完结，下节我想给大家展示一个针对认证加密系统的
segment. In the next segment I want to
show you another very, very clever attack on
非常聪明的攻击
authenticated encryption systems.